Guide to the James J. John papers, circa 1930-2016,
John, James J. papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James J. John papers, circa 1930-2016, bulk 1970-2010.
14-17-4295
James, John, 1928-
11 cubic feet.
Research material, photographs, publications, audio recordings
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Materials relating to the career of Professor James John. Items relate to medieval studies including intellectual history and universities, theology, Latin paleography, historiography, Preand#x301;montreand#x301;. Course materials including, lectures, notes, syllabi, exams, and annotated publications for his courses in the Department of History including courses on the Middle Ages, medieval culture 400-1300 and paleography. Files relating to History 263, 264, 365, 366, 501, and 665. Publications owned by or relating to Harry Caplan, Dorothy Schullian, John J. Waldemer. Many slides and images of medieval and other manuscripts some of which have been digitized. Materials from and relating to E. A. (Elias Avery) Lowe including a set of glass lantern slides of medieval manuscripts belonging to Lowe, correspondence, publications, transcriptions of manuscripts, biographical material.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
James John is a Cornell University professor emeritus, where he taught medieval intellectual history; historiography; universities; Latin paleography in the Department of History.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Materials relating to the career of Professor James John. Items relate to medieval studies including intellectual history and universities, theology, Latin paleography, historiography, Preand#x301;montreand#x301;. Course materials including, lectures, notes, syllabi, exams, and annotated publications for his courses in the Department of History including courses on the Middle Ages, medieval culture 400-1300 and paleography. Files relating to History 263, 264, 365, 366, 501, and 665. Publications owned by or relating to Harry Caplan, Dorothy Schullian, John J. Waldemer. Many slides and images of medieval and other manuscripts some of which have been digitized. Materials from and relating to E. A. (Elias Avery) Lowe including a set of glass lantern slides of medieval manuscripts belonging to Lowe, correspondence, publications, transcriptions of manuscripts, biographical material.
SUBJECTS
Names:
John, James, 1928-; Caplan, Harry, 1896-1980.; Lowe, E. A. (Elias Avery), 1879-1969.; Schullian, Dorothy M. (Dorothy May), 1906-1989.
Subjects:
Historiography.; Medievalism -- Study and teaching.; Middle Ages -- Study and teaching.; Paleography.; Paleography, Latin.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Additional Dorothy Schullian material located in collection #4131, Dorothy May Schullian papers.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Coursework
Series II. E.A. Lowe files
Series III. Slides, films, and microfilms
Series IV. General documents
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Coursework
  - Subseries Ia. History 263 and 303
    - Hist 263 and 303: Lecture 3, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 4 Origin Growth and Organization of Christianity, Expression (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hist 263: Rise of the Papacy, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 5 Monasticism, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 6 The Age of the Fathers, 1979-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 7 St. Augustine, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hist 263: Humility in the City of God, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 9 The Barbarians, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 9 Codex Argenteus, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 10 The Byzantine Empire and Its Separation from Western Europe, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 11 Mohammed and the Spread of Islam, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 12 Early Medieval Art, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 12 Early Medieval Literature, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Hist 263: The Earlier Middle Ages, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 15 Ireland, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 16 England, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 16 England, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 17 The Realinment of European Political relationships in the Mid-Eighth Century, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Hist 263 and 303 Exams, 1967-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Hist 263 References, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hist 263 References, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Hist 263: Lecture The Carolingian Empire, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 19 Charlegmane, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Hist 263: Carolingian Latin Poetry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hist 263: Carolingian Renaissance, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 22 Carolingian Renaissance Art, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hist 263: Carolingian Renaissance III, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 25 The Decline of the Carolingian Empire and the Onslaughts of the Moslems [sic], Vikings, and Hungarians, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hist 263: Ottonian Age, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 27 Feudalism, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 28 The Church in Feudal Society, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 30 Feudal Nobility and The Song of Roland, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 28 Manorialism and Serfs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 30-31 The Age of Gregory VII, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hist 263: The Gregorian Epoch II, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Hist 263: Lecture 33 The Normans and Still Further Expansion of Europe, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Hist 263: The Bayeux Tapestry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Hist 263: Growth of Town and Trade, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Hist 263: Technology Part 1, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Hist 263 Notes, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Hist 303: Introduction/Syllabi, 1967-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Hist 263: The Roman Background, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Hist 263: Introduction, Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Subseries Ib. History 336 and 366
    - Faculty of Theology Notes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XIV Scholastic Methods, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XV Scholastic Method Disputation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XVII Scholastic Method Summa (Thomas Aquinas), Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XIX Scholasticism and Science, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXV Scholasticism and History, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XI History and the Medieval University, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XVI The Relation of Reason and Revelation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XVIII Authority, Academic Freedom, and Christian Institutions, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XX Medieval Universities on their Own History, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXI Scholasticism and Classical Literature, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXVIII 12th Century Latin Literature, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXVI Scholasticism and Gothic Architecture, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Hist 336: Dante, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXVI Disputation on Eternity of the World, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XX Scholasticism and Political Philosophy, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXIV Dictamen, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXIII Determinates, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXII Disputation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XXVI Beyond Scholasticism, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hist 336: Final Exams, 1964-1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Disputatio de Aboetione, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Hist 366: Syllabi and Miscellaneous, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Hist 336/366: Introduction, Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Hist 336: Miscellaneous, 1965-1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Hist 366: Introduction, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Hist 336: Lecture II Background, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - A Pre-Scholastic Synthesis Hugh of Saint Victor, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Hist 336: Lecture IX Translations from Greek and Arabic, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Hist 366: Master's New Vocation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hist 336: Lecture V Teacher Power and Paris, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Hist 336: Lecture VI University Personnel The Students, Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Hist 336: Lecture VII Student Power and Bologna, Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Hist 336: Lecture VIII The Curriculum, Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - The Medieval University Curriculum From Arts to Philosophy and Its Christian Dimension, Undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Hist 336: Lecture X Faculty of Arts From Liberal Arts to Philosophy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Hist 336: Lecture XI Medicine, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries Ic. History 365
    - Hist 365: Syllabi and Miscellaneous, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 1 Introduction, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 2 Survey of Monastic Constitutional History, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 3 Monastic Constitutional Survey, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 4 Monastic Constitutional Survey Cluny to Citeaux, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Hist 365: Survey Concluded, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 6 Horarium, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Hist 365: Manual Labor, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 8 Lectio Divina, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Hist 365: Lecture 9 Lectio Divina, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Hist 365: Opus Dei, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Hist 365: Monasticism, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Hist 365: Schools, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Hist 365: Architecture and Sculpture, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hist 365: Painting, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Hist 365: Music, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hist 365: Literature, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hist 365: Hagiography, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Hist 365: Historiography, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hist 365: Philosophy of History, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Hist 365: Philosophy, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Hist 365: Theology, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hist 365: Medieval Culture Conclusion, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Hist 365: Syllabi and Exams, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hist 365: Syllabi and Miscellaneous, 1974-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hist 365: Isidorous of Seville, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Hist 365: Exams, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Subseries Id. History 335
    - Hist 335: Lecture I Introduction, 1968-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hist 335: Lecture II Greek Background, 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Hist 335: Lecture III Latin Background, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Hist 335: Lecture IV Christianity Conversion of the Intellectuals, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Augustine's Writings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Hist 335: Lecture V Nature, Grace, and the Miraculous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Hist 335: Lecture VI Christianity and Classical Culture, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Hist 335: Lecture VII Christianity and the Secular World, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hist 335: Lecture VIII Monasticism, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Hist 335: Lecture X Barbarianism and Christianity, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Hist 335: Lecture IX Boethius, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XII England, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XIII Germany, Undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XIV Preliminary Exams, 1964-1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XV Carolingians I, Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XVII Carolingians III The Arts, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Literature and Education (Carolingian), Undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Hist 335: Carolingian Political Theology, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Carolingian Historiography, Undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Carolingian Vernacular Literature, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XIX Ottonians, Cultural "Drang nach Osten", Undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XX Cluny, Undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXI The Epic and the Feudal Ideal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXII Gregorian Reform, Undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXIII Intellectual Revival of the 11th Century, Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXIV In Pursuit of Jerusalem, Undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXV Role of Medieval Underdogs 1. Women, Undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXVII Romanesque Art, Undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Hist 335: Lecture XXVIII Synthesis of Hugh of St. Victor, Undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Hist 335: Carolingian and Romanesque Architecture, Undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Early Medieval Art, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Medieval Sculpture, Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Misc Medieval Culture Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Subseries Ie. History 263
    - Hist 263: Ireland "enters" Europe, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Subseries If. History 501
    - Hist 501: Philosophy of Historiography Nature of Historical Explanations, Undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Hist 501: Philosophy of Historiography Causal Judgements and Values, Undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Hist 501: Auxiliary Sciences, Undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Hist 501: Auxiliary Sciences- Paleography, Undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Hist 501: Philosophy of History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Hist 501: Herodotus, Undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Hist 501: Machiavelli, Undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Hist 501: Niebuhr, Undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Oral History, 1966-1971 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Hist 501: Archaeology and History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Hist 501: Contemporary History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Hist 501: Economic History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Hist 501: History of Education, Undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Hist 501: Geography and History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Hist 501: Intellectual History, 1949-1962 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Hist 501: Local History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Hist 501: Philosophy of Historiography Objectivity or Relativity, 1932-1934 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Hist 501: Moral Judgements in History, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Hist 501: Public Opinion, Undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Hist 501: Biography, Undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Hist 501: Quantification, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hist 501: Social Sciences, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Hist 501: Universal History, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hist 501: Ranke, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Hist 501: Thucydides, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hist 501: Toynbee, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Hist 501: More Bloch, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Hist 501: Gibbon, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Medieval Institute Notre Dame, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Map of Central Europe, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Hist 501: Auxiliary Sciences: Philology, Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Bibliography on Medieval Historiography, Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Bodelser Antirle: Carbon, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Monasticism I, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Misc. Slide Documents, Undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Speculum: A Journal of Medieval Studies, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Gotik in Slowenian, 1995-10 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Latin Paleography Documents, Undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Latin Paleography Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Hist 664-665: Latin Paleography, 1970-1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Paleographie, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Subseries Ig. History 665
    - Hist 665: Latin Paleography, 1981-1986 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Paleography Bibliography, Undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous Paleographies, Undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Nicolai de Cusa Compendium, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Hist 665: Final Exam, 1999-05-19 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous Documents, Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Paleograpy Documents, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Series II. E.A. Lowe files
  - Miscellaneous Journals, 1931-1967 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Journals, 1913-1977 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Journals, 1926-1978 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - E.A. Lowe Biography, Undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1966-1995 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Oversized List of Texts, Undated (Box Map Case, Folder 1)
- Series III. Slides, films, and microfilms
  - Miscellaneous Film, Undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous Postcards, Undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Paleographic Slide Notes, Undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Film from Germany, Undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Slides, Graphology, Microfilm, Undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Slide Digitization Notes, Undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Slides, Undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Slides, Undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous Slides, Undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Orvieto Tape, Undated; TR-15868 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Cassette
  - Treasures of Irish Art, Undated; TR-15869 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Carmina Burana, Undated; TR-15870 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Late Antique and Early Christian Art, Undated; TR-15871 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Unnamed Tape Recording, Undated; TR-15872 (Box 7)
    Reel-to-Reel Recording
  - Box A Slides: Paris, Germany, England/Ireland, Undated (Box 7)
  - Box B Slides: London; Chichester Reliefs Set 14, Robert de Lindeseye Psalter Set 15; New York; Morgan Library; Middle East, Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 7)
  - Box C Slides: Miscellaneous, Yale University, Undated (Box 7)
  - Box D Slides: Miscellaneous, Orvieto, Late Antique and Early Christian Art, Barockkirche Ochsenhausen, Vaux Bastille, Undated (Box 7)
  - Box E Slides: Miscellaneous, Iceland, Burgos Cathedral, Miscellaneous Maps, France, Undated (Box 7)
  - Box F Slides: Miscellaneous, England, France; Paris, Germany, Eastern Europe/Middle East, Ravenna, Art, Undated (Box 7)
  - Box G Slides: Rome, Florida, Undated (Box 7)
  - 12 Slides: Color Memories, Koln/Cologne, Undated (Box 7)
  - 12 Slides: Souvenir, Villa dei Misteri Pompei Scavi, Undated (Box 7)
  - 36 Color Slides: Souvenir Ravenna 37-72, Undated (Box 7)
  - 36 Color Slides: Souvenir Ravenna 1-36, Undated (Box 7)
  - 60 Color Slides: Souvenir Roma, Undated (Box 7)
  - 60 Color Slides: Souvenir Ravenna 49-120, Undated (Box 7)
  - 60 Color Slides: Souvenir Roma, Undated (Box 7)
  - 24 Color Slides: Souvenir Pisa, Undated (Box 7)
  - Compendium Historiae, Undated (Box 7)
    Microfilm
  - Multiple Microfilms: History of Steph. Bodek, Undated (Box 7)
  - Bibliotheca Praemonstratensis (Misc Pages), Undated (Box 7)
  - Latin Folio 305 and Theology Folio 186, Undated (Box 7)
  - Klonsterneuburg Mg. 440, Undated (Box 7)
  - Durham Cathedral Library, Undated (Box 7)
  - M 32 Cambridge University Library Arnold of Geylhorn (?), Undated (Box 7)
  - Paris, B.N. Mss Latin 14414 and 14417, Undated (Box 7)
  - Paris, B.N. Latin 16390 and Latin 15449, Undated (Box 7)
  - Paris, B.N Latin 16481 and Latin 15903, Undated (Box 7)
  - 3 Miscellaneous Microfilms, Undated (Box 7)
  - Cabridge- Corpus Christi College Ms 103, Undated (Box 7)
  - Stephan Bodeber, Troctalus Decem Preceptorum, Undated (Box 7)
  - Munich CLM17272 William Oberndorffer, Undated (Box 7)
  - Lecturae sup. Decretum et Decretales in studio Pragensi, Undated (Box 7)
  - Berlin Folios 720, 9r-12r, 13r-16r, Undated (Box 7)
  - Notre Dame, IN Microfilm, Undated (Box 7)
  - Florence Folios 1r-14r, 238v-309v, Undated (Box 7)
  - Gilbertus Tornacensis, Rudimentum Doctrinae Edinburgh 9 mm. Libr. Ms. 111, Undated (Box 7)
  - Oxford, Bodleian Ms. Digby 204, Undated (Box 7)
  - Berlin, Theological Folios 572, 77-278, Undated (Box 7)
  - Clm 15331, 17272, 24836, Undated (Box 7)
  - Art on Wilsnock, Undated (Box 7)
  - E.A. Lowe Lantern Slides in wooden box, Undated (Box 9)
  - Negatives of Greek and Syriac Plates for Mt. Sinai Psalter, Undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Cellulose Film Slides, Undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
- Series IV. General documents
  - CLA History MSS, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - University of Toulouse Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Historiography and Rhetoric Clippings, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Vitae Sanctorum, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Adam of Bremen, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Arnold of Geylhoven Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Augustine Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Scans, Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bernard Gai Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bonaventine's Meditationes Vitae Christe and Factual Truth, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Boncompagni Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Einhard Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Eusebius Notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Gervase of Canterbury Works, Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Gregory of Tours Works, Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Guibert de Nogent, Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Jerome Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Joachim Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Jordanes Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Matthew Paris Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Nicholas Trivet Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Nithard Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Ordericus Vitalis Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Orosius Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Otto of Friesing Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Paul the Deacon Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Peter Comestor Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Hist 635 Documents, 1967-01 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Premonstratension Historiography, Undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Ptolomy of Lucca Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Raymond of Capua Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Rolandinus of Padua Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Sigebert of Gembloux, Undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Vincent of Beuvais, Undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - William of Malmesbury Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - William of Tyre Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Greek Historians, Undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Historical Methods- Synthesis, Undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Historical Methods- Presentation or Exposition, Undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1930-1961 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1953-1961 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1929-1943 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Speculum: A Journal of Medieval Studies, 1946-1979 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1935-1978 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1941-1968 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1948-1968 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous Historiographs, Undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1930-1970 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Carol Kaske Publications, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 41)